When you encode text into binary
it's often nice to use as little data as possible
So you might naturally wonder: is there some kind of fundamental limit on how efficiently text can be compressed
The default encoding with ASCII is pretty inefficient
Each character is represented with eight full bits
If you apply a little cleverness
associating more common characters with smaller bitstrings
you can get this down to an average of around four bits per character
And then much smarter methods than that
that leverage patterns among long sequences of text
can get even better still
But again
what's the limit
I'm guessing many of you might have heard an estimate here
I will share one at the end
But much more interesting than any single numerical answer is how you would even approach answering it
This question dates back at least the 1940s
with Claude Shannon's seminal work that kicked off information theory
Now what's very interesting is how the math that he developed to answer questions like this has turned out to be surprisingly useful for modern machine learning
To take the salient example of today
when large language models are trained
the pre-training portion of that is usually described as being about next-token prediction
specifically using something called cross-entropy loss
Now that term
cross-entropy
has its roots in information theory
But what's also interesting is that one of the conclusions of information theory says that prediction and compression are mathematically equivalent
They turn out to be two sides of the same coin
which means you can entirely reframe how you think about the pre-training objective as not really being about next-token prediction per se
but instead as being about creating the most efficient possible text compressor
Later
I'll explain exactly how that works
But when you do
I think it offers more clarity on what this notion of cross-entropy really is and why you're using it
Also
I don't know about you
but to me at least
there's just something very intriguing about using compression as a fundamental objective while pursuing intelligence
In fact
some people have gone so far as to say compression is intelligence